

# **SAGAR TALOD**

# Software Development Engineer

6.10 years of experience in software development, building large scale and fault tolerant applications. Strong problem solving and technical skills coupled with confident decision making for enabling effective solutions. Involved in new development and performance optimization of existing functionalities. Successfully managed a small team for timely project deliveries. Good communication skills and experience in handling clients. Worked across various domains like Telecom domain, E-Commerce domain, Procurement domain and finance domain.

+91 8291122228
Kandivali East, Mumbai,
Maharashtra, India
talodsagar@gmail.com

http://www.linkedin.com/in/sagar -talod-7ba331128



# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Associate Technical Delivery Manager (Morgan Stanley)

Accolite Digital, Mumbai, India Oct 2023 – Present

Software Development Engineer

> **Jio**, Mumbai, India May 2022 – Sep 2023

Tech Lead – Java Development

**Zycus,** Mumbai, India July 2019 – May 2022

**Associate Software Engineer** 

Logixal Solutions Pvt Ltd, Mumbai, India March 2017 – May 2019

- Migration of legacy application into existing microservice.
- Bug Fixing and monitoring existing applications.
- Build and deployment using Jenkins.
- Technologies used are Java, Spring boot, REST, Kafka, Redis Cache, Sybase, MongoDB, Jenkins, Splunk, Linux.
- Built a product from scratch to block moonlighting with respect to Customer Care Agent.
- Application consists of APIs to store Agent data and to create a set of voice recording periodically, compare these data for validation based on scheduled time and notify in case of moonlighting.
- Implemented utility service to support continuous file upload to SFTP server based on schedule.
- Bug Fixing and monitoring existing applications.
- Build and deployment using Azure Devops.
- Technologies used are Java, Spring boot, Spring Security, REST, Kafka, Redis Cache, Oracle, MongoDB, Docker, Kubernetes, Linux.
- Built an application that provides a configurable data integration mapping between Zycus client and Zycus product. Used an open-source library JOLT and integrated it within current application with lots of added features which are specific to Zycus requirements.
- Built a complete business-oriented solution for Zycus integration. Developed integration interfaces to integrate Zycus products with client ERP via SFTP.
- Developed integration interfaces to consume REST API, transform data into specific format.
   It consists of 5 microservices using technologies like Java, Spring Boot, Spring Security, Spring Scheduler, Quartz, GoogleDAO, Redis cache, REST, ActiveMQ, Consul, CICD, Jenkins.
- Resolving bugs and providing support on existing services.
- Created different webservices to cater ongoing and new requirements on Ecommerce domain products.
- Added Authentication to existing endpoints, added rate limiter to control the traffic on application and worked on other requirements and changes.
- Application support, defect fixing and worked on various monitoring tools.
- Automation using Selenium Java to generate report from monitoring tools like New Relic, Sumologic, MPulse, Tealeaf.
- Ant build and Manual deployment on Tomcat server.
- Technologies used are Oracle ATG Commerce 11.3, Java, SMTP, JavaScript, jQuery, AJAX, SVN, SQL, WebLogic and Linux.

#### Skills

- Have worked across domains such as e-commerce, procurement, telecom.
- Understanding of Agile software development principles and experience working in Agile/Scrum teams.
- Strong command of the Java programming language, including its core features, objectoriented principles, data structures, and algorithms. Worked on various Java frameworks
  and libraries, such as Spring boot, Security, Hibernate, JPA, etc., used for web
  development, enterprise applications, desktop applications, etc.
- Ability to design and implement RESTful APIs using Java to facilitate communication between different systems.
- Knowledge of working with databases, including SQL queries, and familiarity with database management systems like MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, or NoSQL databases like MongoDB.
- Worked on testing frameworks and good understanding on debugging and troubleshooting complex issues in Java applications.
- Experience with version control systems like Git, SVN, including branching, merging, and pull requests.
- Familiarity with build tools such as Maven, Ant to manage project dependencies and automate the build process.
- Understanding and application of common design patterns like Singleton, Factory, etc., to write scalable and maintainable code.
- Knowledge of handling concurrency and multithreading challenges in Java applications.
- Ability to optimize Java code for better performance and efficiency, including memory management and avoiding performance bottlenecks.
- Awareness of Java application security best practices, such as secure authentication mechanisms, input validation, and protection against common vulnerabilities.
- Worked on CI/CD tools for continuous development, and deployment processes.
- Strong problem-solving and analytical abilities to tackle complex technical challenges.
- Good written and verbal communication skills to document code, communicate with team members, and collaborate effectively.

# **Education**

MBA 2020 – 2023

CDAC 2016 – 2017

Engineering 2013 – 2016

Diploma 2008 – 2013

- MBA in Information Technology, Mumbai University (Part Time)
   Jamnalal Bajaj Institute of Management Studies, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India.
- PG-Diploma in Advanced Computing
   MET Institute of Information Technology, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India.
- Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Engineering, Mumbai University
   SSPM's College of Engineering and Technology, Kankavali, Maharashtra, India
- Diploma in Computer Technology, Maharashtra State Board of Technical Education KVM IT Polytechnic, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India

# **Projects**

- Morgan Stanley, India
- Reliance Jio, India
- iConsole Zycus, India
- Liverpool Suburbia, Mexico
- Pride Mobility, US
- AAFES, US
- Beth Bath and Beyond, US
- Others

# Technology Used

- Spring Boot, Microservices, Spring Security, Consul Service Discovery, Docker, Kubernetes, Nexus, JFrog
- Java/J2EE, Multithreading, REST, MQ, Kafka, Redis cache, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, AJAX
- Oracle, PostgreSQL, Microsoft SQL Server, My SQL, MongoDB
- JBOSS, WebLogic, Apache Tomcat

### **Tools Used**

- IntelliJ, Eclipse, Postman, SOAP UI, Putty, WinSCP, SQL Developer
- Jira, Azure, Salesforce
- Git, SVN
- Microsoft Excel, Word, Power Point
- Windows, Linux